Ellinor Porcher Gadsden Papers WLU.Coll.0189
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Ellinor Porcher Gadsden Papers
Inclusive 1839-1975
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Gadsden, Ellinor Porcher
Johnston, Joseph E. (Joseph Eggleston), 1807-1891
Preston, Margaret Junkin
Pendleton, Lella
Lee, Mildred Childe, 1846-1905
Pendleton, William Nelson, 1809-1883
Pendleton, Alexander Swift
Pendleton family
WLU.Coll.0189
1 Linear Feet 2.3 linear ft.
Scope and Contents
This collection came from the estate of Ellinor Gadsden in 1985. Highlights of the collection include the letters of Alexander Swift(Sandie) Pendleton, a Washington College graduate who was a top aide to Thomas Jonathan "Stonewall" Jackson during the American Civil War. These approximately 70 letters were a major source for the book. Sandie was the uncle of the Gadsden sisters. Included in the collection are also a few items of Gen. William Nelson Pendleton who was Robert E. Lee's friend and colleague. There are two ALS of Mildred Lee to Lella Pendleton and two copies of a poem written by and in the hand of Margaret Junkin Preston. There is also an ALS (25 Jan. 1873) from Gen. Joseph E. Johnston to W.N. Pendleton. Other major parts of the collection are photographs (ca. 60), the Misses Gadsden's account books and their memorabilia from their travels.
Biographical / Historical
Ellinor was the twin sister of Anzolette Pendleton Gadsden. Ellinor worked for a number of years at the Washington and Lee University library and her sister worked at the Virginia Military Institute library. They also rented rooms at The Pines which was their home on Lee Avenue located in Lexington, Va.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Estate of Ellinor P. Gadsden.
Correspondence; Printed ephemera; Photographs; Travel; Poetry; Biography; Personal Narratives; United States -- Confederate States of America; Lee, Susan Pendleton
- Control Folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
- William Nelson Pendleton- Episcopal High School Recorder, 1839-1843 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- (A.S.) Sandie Pendleton Letters, 1856-1859 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- (A.S.) Sandie Pendleton: Cincinnati Oration, 1857-07-02 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- (A.S.) Sandie Pendleton as president of University Cricket Club, 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- (A.S.) Sandie Pendleton Letters, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- (A.S.) Sandie Pendleton Letters, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- (A.S.) Sandie Pendleton Letters, 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- (A.S.) Sandie Pendleton Letters, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- (A.S.) Sandie Pendleton Letters, No Dates (Box 1, Folder 10)
- (A.S.) Sandie Pendleton Letter to George Junkin, No Date (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Rose Pendleton: Copied account from her diary of "The Yankees in Lexington", 1864 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Mary Junkin Preston: printed poem "Epithalamium", 1878-10-10 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- John Thomas Lewis Preston ALS to Dr. and Mrs. Pendleton, 1881-07-13 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Mary Junkin Preston: Poem to Dr. and Mrs. Pendleton, 1881-07-13; 1882-07-15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Rev. and Mrs. W.N. Pendleton 50th anniversary invitation, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence and Documents, 1860-1897 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- 2 ALS from Mildred Lee to Leila Pendleton, No Dates (Box 1, Folder 18)
- 19th Century Miscellany (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence (Business), 1918-1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Tax Receipts: Town and County, 1920-1934 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- 20th Century Miscellany (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Memorabilia: Invitation from President Theodore Roosevelt, 1905-01-12; 1905-02-09 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Memorabilia: Stamps (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Clippings of Family (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Miscellaneous Accounts, 1925-1966 (Box 2)
- Income Account Book, 1954-1968 (Box 2)
- Private Account Book, 1945-1955 (Box 2)
- Income Account Book, 1939-1953 (Box 2)
- Pines Account Book, 1965-1970 (Box 2)
- Pines Account Book, 1954-1959 (Box 2)
- Pines Account Book, 1959-1964 (Box 2)
- Framed carte de visite of Mary Custis Lee by Micheal Miley, c. 1872 (Box 3)
  Scope and Contents
  Inscribed from Mrs. Lee to Mary Nelson Pendleton
- Miniature Book- Gentle Thoughts, 1860-1880 (Box 3)
- 1/6 plate daguerreotype of Susan Pendleton Lee, 1850-1857 (Box 3)
- Printer's block of image of Susan Pendleton Lee, 1900-1930 (Box 3)
- Photographs- Houston and Pattie Barclay (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Photographs- Ted Barclay Jr. and Friends (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Photographs- Ellinor Porcher and Anzolette Pendleton (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Photographs- Edwin Gray Lee (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Photographs- Susan Pendleton Lee (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Photographs- Lawrence and Edmund Lee (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Photographs- Sandie Pendleton (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Photographs- William Nelson Pendleton (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Photographs- The Pines (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Photographs- Unidentified Places (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Photographs- Unidentified People (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Photographs- Miscellaneous (identified) (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Photographs - Stereoviews
  - Stereoview of the Crystal Palace, London, England, 1869-1878; This stereoview card is hand colored.
    Crystal Palace (Great Exhibition, 1851, London, England)
- Photographs- Pencil drawing (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Facsimiles of various documents (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Includes a 1781 letter of General Christopher Gadsden
- Prints of sites in Europe (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Print from Godey Ladies Book (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Drawings of Lee and generals (prints) (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Framed picture of General and Mrs. Lee (Box 3)
- Framed portrait of Mrs. Lee (Box 3)
- Postcards (Box 4)
  This box contains souvenir postcards (approximiately 350)and some related ephemera from the Gadsden sisters' European travels in 1931. There are about 25 American cards including Lexington, Va. scenes.
  - Materials Related to S.S. Leviathan, 1931
    Eastern Steamship Line; Leviathan (Ship)
    - S.S. Leviathan Passanger List (two copies)
    - Ship Dinner Menu for June 22, 1931 (two copies)
    - Ship Lunch Menu for August 16, 1931 (two copies)
    - Ship Menus and Entertainment Programs, 1931-06-21; 1931-08-14; 1931-06-22; 1931-09-15; 1931-06-18
  - Various Postcards
    - Wide Collection of Post Cards from Europe, 1900-1935
    - 16 American Post Cards, Various Locations
    - Postcard of the "Le Paqubot" of the Normandie Line, 1937-06-17
      Normandie Shipping Line. Le Paquebot
    - 8 Postcards of Lexington, Virginia and other VA Locations
    - 14 Luggage Labels from the S.S. Leviathan (3 Different Designs)